FABIAN RETANA

CONTACT

↓ +506 6440-5384

✓ fabian.retana@gmail.com

↑ https://github.com/fabian-rh



I am a Software developer with enterprise experience creating and implementing code changes on large transactional applications based on Java and React following best coding practices and patterns. Additionally, I have experience in front-end and back-end development using tools such as IBM SQL, Java, Struts, Spring, and Azure cloud services, with expertise in user interfaces React, Typescript, and Redux. I've also worked with Powershell script building and Azure DevOps CI/CD pipelines. In my latest project, we are rewriting a large financial application to a modern UI Framework like React, Typescript, and Redux, which has been an amazing opportunity to increase my knowledge and polish my programming skills.

SKILLS

- Java, Typescript, Javascript
- Spring, Springboot, Struts, React, Redux
- Eclipse, VsCode, IntelliJ IDEA.
- Git, Github, RTC repo and version management.
- Script shell with powershell.
- Cloud experience with Azure, certified
- IBM DB2 SQL server.
- HTML5, CSS, Scss, Carbon UI, TSX
- Excellent English and Communication Skills, ability to communicate clearly.
- Experience with Agile methodologies.

SOFT SKILLS

- Growth mindset and always looking for new learning opportunities.
- Demonstrated problem solving skills.
- Analytical skills
- Passion for new topics and Learning-Oriented
 Mindset
- Excellent team work and collaborative approach towards problem solving.

CERTIFICATIONS

- Microsoft Certified: Azure Cloud Fundamentals ID I132-4891
- AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner

EDUCATION

Bachelor's Degree Software Engineering

Cenfotec University

Jan 2021

Data Analyst Technical Degree

Costa Rica's Institute of Technology (ITCR) Dec 2020

EXPERIENCE

IBM

May 2022 - Current

Oct 2023 - Current

React Software Developer

- IBM Fintech and Finance Team, large financial application for banks and government
- Experience with React, Redux, React Hook Forms, Typescript, TSX, Html 5, Scss , Carbon UI
- Experience designing, developing and testing new Front-end pages that follow our visual design patterns and have full interaction with server and our Backend Api
- Responsible for successful implementation of complex business logic in the UI
- Responsible for Bug fixing, debugging and testing the application
- Experience with Redux for Api Endpoints implementations and RTK state management
- Experience with building the redux server side of the application to implement the connections to the APIs and also implement the UI pages based on Typescript, Html, Tsx, Scss Css
- React testing frameworks, Jest, Node-Fetch and mock testing for the UI and Redux server API
- Follow best coding practices and excellent knowledge of design patterns and algorithms
- Great relation with my peers and closely worked with our backend developers

Software Developer

Jan 2023 - Oct 2023

- Large financial application running on Java 8, Struts Java Framework and J2EE servers for backend and Dojo Javascript and JSPs for UI side.
- Experience implementing new Java based functionalities based on our sprint and story goals
- Worked with Core Java and Framework configs, also implemented DB2 accessors.
- Experience working with Sql DB2, navigating through complex relations and implementing the appropriate changes based business needs.
- Responsible for fixing vulnerabilities from PenTesters and security reports
- Experience working with Javascript for the UI side of the application, also with code refactoring based on business needs and changes done to the Java backend and Sql DB2 Database
- Worked with Java Backend RESTful services and WebSphere web server.
- Ensured reliable and well-tested deployments as part of the development process.
- Good interpersonal and communication skills, ability to reach across squads and Senior members of our teams to perform and implement all tasks and testing in a successful manner.

Java Software Developer

Jun 2022 - Nov 2022

- Worked on POC for internal project based on Java Spring and Springboot
- \bullet Experience with Java 17 and Springboot Framework for developing Rest endpoints
- \bullet Used IBM's internal JDBC implementation for accesing and manipulating data in Database
- Developed and implemented Rest services in Springboot to interact with DB2
- Used Junit and Mock testing for thorough testing of code implementations.

• Experience with Sql queries and syntax, Git and Github

Mckinsey & Co.

Aug 2014 - May 2022

IT Analyst

Alyst Feb 2020 - May 2022

- •Internal Windows App Store, in charge of App Scripting and deployments via DevOps
- $\bullet \text{Experience with Powershell to automate the App installation process and silently install / delete} \\$
- $\bullet {\sf Experience \ using \ Azure \ Devops \ CI\ /\ CD\ pipelines \ for \ application \ deployment \ and \ configuration.}$
- Responsible for testing and succesfully deploying new Apps to the App Store
 Experience with Xml and Json configuration files.

IT Advanced Support Specialist

Sept 2016 - Jan 2020

- •Deployment and Support for large Applications with over twenty thousand users
- •Experience with Mobileiron iOS Mobile Management Framework
- •Experience with Windows Server configurations and Uniflow printing system

IT Specialist

Aug 2014 - Oct 2016

• Desktop Application support, Windows 10, MacOS, Ms Office and Lotus Notes